<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN"
    "http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/xml-forrest/src/core/context/resources/schema/dtd/document-v12.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>FOP: Configuration</title>
    <version>$Revision$</version>
  </header>

  <body>
  <section id="general">
    <title>Configuration File Basics</title>
    <p>The FOP configuration file is an XML file containing a variety of settings that are useful for controlling FOP's behavior, and for helping it find resources that you wish it to use.</p>
    <p>The easiest way to get started using a FOP configuration file is to copy the sample found at <code>{fop-dir}/conf/userconfig.xml</code> to a location of your choice, and then to edit it according to your needs.
It contains templates for the various configuration options, most of which are commented out. Remove the comments and change the settings for entries that you wish to use.
Be sure to follow any instructions, including comments which specify the value range.
Also, since the configuration file is XML, be sure to keep it well-formed.</p>
    <note>Do <strong>not</strong> change <code>{fop-dir}/conf/config.xml</code> or use it as the basis for your configuration file. It has an entirely different purpose.</note>
    <section id="general-entries">
      <title>Creating Entries</title>
      <p>The general structure of the configuration file is a series of &lt;entry> tags, each containing a &lt;key> and a &lt;value>. (Fonts use a different format). Here is an example:</p>
      <source><![CDATA[<entry>
  <key>strokeSVGText</key>
  <value>false</value>
</entry>]]></source>
    </section>
    <section id="general-available">
      <title>Making Configuration Available to FOP</title>
      <p>After creating your configuration file, you must tell FOP how to find it:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>If running FOP from the command-line, see the "-c" command-line option in <link href="running.html">Running FOP</link>.</li>
        <li>If running FOP as an embedded application, see <link href="embedding.html#config-external">FOP: Embedding, Using a Configuration File</link>.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>See <link href="embedding.html#config-internal">Setting the Configuration Programmatically</link> for instructions on how to do so in an embedded environment.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="summary-key-value">
    <title>Summary of Key-Value Configuration Options</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Option (key)</th>
        <th>Data Type (for the value)</th>
        <th>Default Value</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>baseDir</td>
        <td>URL</td>
        <td>For command-line, the directory containing the input FO or XML file. For embedded, the current working directory.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>fontBaseDir</td>
        <td>URL</td>
        <td>value of baseDir</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><link href="#hyphenation-dir">hyphenation-dir</link></td>
        <td>URL</td>
        <td>None. This is for custom hyphenation patterns.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><link href="#svg-strokeSVGText">strokeSVGText</link></td>
        <td>Boolean</td>
        <td>True</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>
  <section id="detail-key-value">
    <title>Detail for Key-Value Configuration Options</title>
    <p>The sections below provide detailed information for configuration options that are not self-explanatory. The parenthetical information after each key name indicates (Data Type, Default).</p>
    <section id="hyphenation-dir">
      <title>hyphenation-dir (URL, none)</title>
      <p>Use this entry to indicate a directory containing custom hyphenation files (if any).
See <link href="hyphenation.html">FOP: Hyphenation</link> for more information on creating and modifying hyphenation within FOP.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="strokeSVGText">
      <title>strokeSVGText (boolean, True)</title>
      <p>In some cases, some text in SVG documents is converted to graphical shapes instead of retaining its character as text. To force all text to be rendered as text, set strokeSVGText = false. For a discussion of this issue, see <link href="graphics.html#svg-pdf-text">FOP: Graphics, Placing SVG Text into PDF</link>.</p>
      <note>strokeSVGText is currently only effective in the PDF renderer.</note>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="fonts">
    <title>Fonts</title>
    <p>Font configuration information is included in the FOP configuration file, but is documented at <link href="fonts.html">FOP: Fonts</link>. Note especially the section entitled <link href="fonts.html#register">Register Fonts with FOP</link>.</p>
  </section>
  </body>
</document>

