<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE Document SYSTEM "Document.dtd">
<Document>
	<Title>SVG in FOP Design</Title>
	<Description>The design for implementing SVG rendering inside FOP. This is out of date.</Description>
	<ExternalChapter file="Todo.xml"/>
	<Chapter>
		<Title>SVG Elements</Title>
		<Section>
			<Title>Purpose</Title>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Background</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						FOP is a formatting object parser written in Java.
					</p>
					<p>
						Apache is heading the effort to create the parser to create
						PDF documents from XML files including formatting objects.
					</p>
					<p>
						SVG is another XML structure type that contains scaleable
						vector graphics. This document is about embedding SVG data
						inside a FOP XML structure so that the SVG will be rendered
						to the resulting PDF document.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Aim</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						The primary aim is to enable the parsing of all SVG elements
						as described in the document "WD-SVG-20000629.pdf". This applies
						to the stylable elements.
					</p>
					<p>
						The java interface is available from -
						"http://www.w3.org/TR/2000/WD-SVG-20000629/java-binding.zip"
					</p>
					<p>
						As the SVG elements include information for animation and
						other things then not all elements or properties will be
						rendered.
					</p>
					<p>
						The implementation should be considered as separate from
						the implementation and rendering of the FOP and PDF data.
						This will allow it to be more general and to be used for
						direct drawing or printing.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
		</Section>
	</Chapter>
	<Chapter>
		<Title>Design</Title>
		<Section>
			<Title>FOP Rendering</Title>
			<ExternalDiagram file="arch-diagrams.xml">fop</ExternalDiagram>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Rendering Process</Title>
				<ExternalDiagram file="arch-diagrams.xml">fop-flow</ExternalDiagram>
				<Body>
					<p>
						The process of converting an FOP XML file into the
						PDF document is handled by the FOP parser.
					</p>
					<p>
						The document is first turned into an in memory hierarchy
						of objects that represent the fo document. The objects are
						then layed out into pages. The objects are then rendered
						into PDF data.
					</p>
					<p>
						These three steps are separate.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
		</Section>
	</Chapter>
	<Chapter>
		<Title>Design</Title>
		<Section>
			<Title>Overall Design of SVG elements</Title>
			<ExternalDiagram file="arch-diagrams.xml">overall</ExternalDiagram>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>SVG Nodes</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						The FObj.layout is called whenever the parser encounters an
						XML node. The class that is called depends on the element
						mapping.
					</p>
					<p>
						The &lt;svg:g&gt; element is used to contain other elements
						including other &lt;svg:g&gt;'s. This element is purely to
						set style and transform data on other elements.
						The GraphicsCreator interface is used to create Graphic
						element that can be placed into the &lt;svg:g&gt; graphic.
					</p>
					<p>
						The &lt;svg:text&gt; element can contain elements that modify
						the position and style of text. The TextElement interface is
						used to create the element which is placed in a list along
						with any strings in the text node.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>SVG Graphic Elements</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						All drawing elements in an SVG area must extend the Graphic
						class. This provides information about the style and transform.
						Transform is accumulative, therefore the transform for a
						particular element is obtained by combining all the transforms
						of the current element and all super elements. A list is
						created by adding each succesive transform into a list.
					</p>
					<p>
						The graphic elements also contain style data, this behaves
						in a different manner. The style for an element is obtained
						by starting with the top ancestor of the element and overriding
						any style elements set in each of the elements in the hierachy.
						This is done by using an style infromation map.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Rendering</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						The main purpose of the SVG elements in this context
						is to be able to render the data to a PDF document.
						This should not limit the approach or the usefullness
						of the SVG in memory data.
					</p>
					<p>
						The data should contain all the available information
						without changing the meaning of elements or properties.
					</p>
					<p>
						The are some examples of data that should be interpreted
						when rendering, or otherwise presenting the data to the user,
						which can be altered and still be eqivalent.
						This includes paths that contain multiple moveto's and
						the closepath part. Since the information is necessary
						for the proper display and editing then the information
						should always be retained with the original meaning.
						The path end points etc differ depending on the path
						instructions.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
		</Section>
	</Chapter>
	<Chapter>
		<Title>Integration</Title>
		<Section>
			<Title>Integration of SVG with FOP</Title>
			<ExternalDiagram file="arch-diagrams.xml">integration</ExternalDiagram>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Areas of Interaction</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						The PDF renderer converts all the FOP data into the
						PDF markup. This is also where the SVG elements are
						output into the PDF stream.
					</p>
					<p>
						The FOP parsing incorporates the idea of areas that
						contain FONode data. These nodes contain the data
						that is rendered into the area. The SVG element
						(&lt;svg:svg&gt; element) forms an area. Then as each
						SVG subnode is parsed it is placed within the SVG area.
						The SVG area then contains a list of Graphic elements
						that constitute the SVG graphic. Almost all Graphic
						elements can have style and transform properties.
						These properties are place into the graphic element.
					</p>
					<p>
						As the &lt;svg:g&gt; element can contain many other
						Graphic elements then it must be able to create and add
						the Graphic to itself as each subnode is parsed.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>XML Specifics</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						An SVG area can be placed within a &lt;fo:block&gt; ??.
						This is provided that the appropriate svg namespace is
						defined.
						All the svg elements must be within the &lt;svg:svg&gt;
						element.
					</p>
					<p>
						When the SVG area is being parsed then it must be able
						to create a representative data set in memory for use
						later.
					</p>
					<p>
						The data must fully represent the information in a way
						that is efficient to create and use.
					</p>
					<p>
						There are a few elements that can contain other elements,
						these include &lt;svg:g&gt;, &lt;svg:text&gt;, &lt;svg:use&gt; etc.
						The FOP parser technique uses <b>layout()</b> to create
						a component and layout it within the area. This is not suitable
						for elements that are not directly sub nodes of the SVG
						area. The technique used is for the SVG elements is to implement
						an interface suitable for the element. For example the Rect
						implements GraphicsCreator so that the parent G can create
						the Graphics object when the parser calls <b>addChild</b>.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Rendering</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						The SVG area contains a list of all the svg elements that can
						be drawn. This list is simply iterated and each element drawn
						in order.
						Each subsequent element always draws over the previous element.
					</p>
					<p>
						The drawing is clipped to the SVG area bounds.
					</p>
					<p>
						As each element may contain its own style and transform
						then before each element is rendered the style and
						coordinate matrix ?? are set if it has changed.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
		</Section>
	</Chapter>
	<Chapter>
		<Title>Design of Components</Title>
		<Section>
			<Title>Graphic Elements</Title>
			<ExternalDiagram file="arch-diagrams.xml">graphic</ExternalDiagram>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Class Hierachy</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						All usual graphic elements that can be drawn in the SVG
						area or a &lt;svg:g&gt; element must extend the Graphic
						class. This serves as a common object type and to hold
						information about the style and transform of the element.
						Since the style and transform inherit information (in a way
						that cannnot be done with simple XML inheritance) then
						each graphic element also stores the parent element (if
						applicable).
					</p>
					<p>
						The text element may contain TSpan elements which are not
						themselves Graphic elements.
					</p>
					<p>
						The SVG area contains the title, description, definitions
						and all the Graphic objects.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Grouping</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						The SVG area contains a list of Graphic elements that
						can be rendered.
					</p>
					<p>
						The SVG area also contains definitions of Graphic
						elements that can be used by other graphic elements
						for clipping, paths etc. The definitions must contain
						a unique id (XML id) which can be used to refer to them.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
		</Section>
		<Section>
			<Title>XML Data</Title>
			<ExternalDiagram file="arch-diagrams.xml">nodes</ExternalDiagram>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Nodes</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						There are two important type of information, these
						are the XML nodes and the properties of these nodes.
						The parsing process used with FOP uses element mapping
						and property mapping to enable the creation of objects
						that correspond to each node or property.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Properties</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						There are a number of important element properties that
						differ and extend the FOP properties.
					</p>
					<p>
						The style and transform properties have particular
						behaviours that are handled through the Graphic object.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Parsing Process</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						There are three steps going from the SVG data (contained
						in the FOP) to the resulting PDF document (or other
						rendering result).
					</p>
					<p>
						When the fop parsing encounters an &lt;svg:svg&gt; element
						then it creates and SVG area object. The layout is called
						for this object which parses all sub nodes. Each sub node
						can then parse its information and add itself to the area.
					</p>
					<p>
						The layout of each node is done before any of the sub nodes
						of the particular node, this means that the information
						for the node is incomplete when it is added to the area.
					</p>
					<p>
						The parsing of the node is converted into a Graphic element
						with its style and transform set. The G element can add the
						Graphic to itself or the element can add itself to the SVG
						area.
					</p>
					<p>
						Once the parsing is complete we have a representation of
						the SVG data in memory. This information can then be used
						to render/manipulate etc.
					</p>
					<p>
						The pdf rendering is done by rendering each element in the
						SVG area. The style is set for the element before it is
						rendered. If the element is a G or text object then each
						sub-element is rendered.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
			<SubSection>
				<Title>Graphic</Title>
				<Body>
					<p>
						<ExternalDiagram file="arch-diagrams.xml">graphic-structure</ExternalDiagram>
						The graphic elements (almost) all contain style and transform
						data. This is stored in a way that allows the information
						to be combined when determining the style/transform for an element
						with style/transform set in one or more ancestors.
					</p>
				</Body>
			</SubSection>
		</Section>
	</Chapter>
</Document>
