<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN"
    "http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/xml-forrest/src/resources/schema/dtd/document-v11.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Compiling FOP</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Do You Need To Compile?</title>
      <p>FOP distributions are either pre-compiled binary or source.
If you are using a binary distribution, it is already compiled and there is no need to compile it again. See the <link href="download.html">Download Instructions</link> for information about whether a binary or source distribution is best for your needs.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Set Up Your Environment</title>
      <section>
        <title>CLASSPATH</title>
        <p>There is no generally no need to setup a classpath.
All libraries needed to compile FOP are included in the source distribution and are referenced by the build script.
You will only need to adjust the classpath if you build FOP in some other way. See the build scripts (build.bat for Windows, and build.sh for Unix) for details.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>JAVA_HOME</title>
        <p>Ant, which is used by the build script, requires that the enviroment variable JAVA_HOME point to your local JDK root directory.
This is true even if you use JDK 1.2 or above, which normally don't need this setting.</p>
      </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Run the "build" Script</title>
    <p>Build FOP by executing the "build" script, which is located in the FOP root directory.
The Windows batch file is build.bat, and the Unix shell script is build.sh.</p>
    <p>The build script uses <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">Ant</link>, a popular java-based build tool.
The file build.xml in the FOP root directory is the blueprint that Ant uses for the build.
Consult its contents for detailed information on the build process and the various build targets.</p>
    <p>A help screen is shown by calling "build usage".</p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <p>If you have problems building FOP, please try the following:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Run the build with the target of "clean", then rerun the build.</li>
      <li>Delete the build directory completely, then rerun the build.</li>
      <li>Make sure you do not have a non-FOP version of xerces.jar, xalan.jar, batik.jar, or another dependency product somewhere in your CLASSPATH.</li>
      <li>If the build still fails, see the <link href="gethelp.html">Getting Help</link> page for further help.</li>
    </ul>
  </section>
  </body>
</document>

