<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN"
    "http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/xml-forrest/src/resources/schema/dtd/document-v11.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>FOP: Configuration</title>
  </header>

  <body>
  <section id="general">
    <title>Configuration File Basics</title>
    <p>The FOP configuration file is an XML file containing a variety of settings that are useful for controlling FOP's behavior, and for helping it find resources that you wish it to use.</p>
    <p>The easiest way to get started using a FOP configuration file is to copy the sample found at <code>{fop-dir}/conf/userconfig.xml</code> to a location of your choice, and then to edit it according to your needs.
It contains templates for the various configuration options, most of which are commented out. Remove the comments and change the settings for entries that you wish to use.
Be sure to follow any instructions, including comments which specify the value range.
Also, since the configuration file is XML, be sure to keep it well-formed.</p>
    <note>Do <strong>not</strong> change <code>{fop-dir}/conf/config.xml</code> or use it as the basis for your configuration file. It has an entirely different purpose.</note>
    <p>The general structure of the configuration file is a series of &lt;entry> tags, each containing a &lt;key> and a &lt;value. (Fonts use a different format). Here is an example:</p>
    <source><![CDATA[<entry>
  <key>strokeSVGText</key>
  <value>false</value>
</entry>]]></source>
    <p>After creating your configuration file, you must tell FOP how to find it:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>If running FOP from the command-line, see the "-c" command-line option in <link href="running.html">Running FOP</link>.</li>
      <li>If running FOP as an embedded application, see <link href="embedding.html#config-external">FOP: Embedding, Using a Configuration File</link>.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>See <link href="embedding.html#config-internal">Setting the Configuration Programmatically</link> for instructions on how to do so in an embedded environment.</p>
  </section>
  <section id="summary-key-value">
    <title>Summary of Key-Value Configuration Options</title>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <th>Option (key)</th>
        <th>Data Type (for the value)</th>
        <th>Default Value</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>baseDir</td>
        <td>URL</td>
        <td>directory containing the input FO file</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>fontBaseDir</td>
        <td>URL</td>
        <td>value of baseDir</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>hyphenation-dir</td>
        <td>URL</td>
        <td>None. This is for custom hyphenation patterns.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><link href="#svg-strokeSVGText">strokeSVGText</link></td>
        <td>Boolean</td>
        <td>True</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </section>
  <section id="hyphenation">
    <title>Setting up hyphenation</title>
    <p>
      FOP comes already with some hyphenation patterns. If you need a hyphenation pattern
      which isn't included in the distribution, do the following:
    </p>
    <ol>
      <li>
Get the TeX hyphenation pattern file and turn it into an xml file which
conforms to the hyphenation.dtd in the subdirectory {fop-dir}/src/hyph.
      </li>
      <li>
Name this new file following this schema: <code>languageCode_countryCode.xml</code>. If
you don't need a country code, leave it out, e.g. the file name for an American
english hyphenation pattern would look like this: <code>en_US.xml</code>. For an Italian 
file: <code>it.xml</code>. Language and country codes must be the same as in XSL-FO, that
is follow
<link href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/pub/ietf/http/related/iso639.txt">ISO 639</link>
and
<link href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/pub/ietf/http/related/iso3166.txt">ISO 3166</link>
respectively. NOTE: The ISO 639/ISO 3166 convention is that language names are
written in lower case, while country codes are written in upper case.
      </li>
      <li>
If you have built your new hyphenation pattern file successfully there are
two ways to make it accessible to FOP.
        <ul>
          <li>
Put this new file into the directory {fop-dir}/src/hyph and rebuild FOP. The file will
be picked up and added to fop.jar.
          </li>
          <li>
Put the file into a directory of your choice and specify this directory
in the userconfig.xml in the entry &lt;hyphenation-dir&gt;.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ol>
    <section id="hyphenation-sources">
      <title>Places to find TeX hyphenation pattern files</title>
      <p>
        The most important place to find hyphenation pattern file is the CTAN TeX Archive:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li><fork href="http://www.ctan.org/tex-archive/language/hyphenation/">CTAN TeX Archive</fork></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <warning>
      You have to carefully check license issues when using hyphenation
      pattern files from other places. The licenses of the files found
      on the Internet are not always clear.
    </warning>
    <note>
      Most of the files published in the CTAN Archive are licenced under the 
      <fork href="http://www.latex-project.org/lppl.html">LaTeX Project Public License (LPPL)</fork>.
      The Apache Foundation can't redistribute files under this license. If you want to use such
      a file you have to decide for yourself if you can use (and possibly distribute) the file under 
      these conditions.
    </note>
  </section>
  <section id="svg">
    <title>SVG</title>
    <section id="svg-strokeSVGText">
      <title>strokeSVGText (boolean, True)</title>
      <p>In some cases, some text in SVG documents is converted to graphical shapes instead of retaining its character as text. To force all text to be rendered as text, set strokeSVGText = false. For a discussion of this issue, see <link href="graphics.html#svg-pdf-text">FOP: Graphics, Placing SVG Text into PDF</link>.</p>
      <note>strokeSVGText is currently only effective in the PDF renderer.</note>
    </section>
  </section>
  </body>
</document>

