<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN"
    "http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/xml-forrest/src/resources/schema/dtd/document-v11.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>FOP: Hyphenation</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section id="hyphenation">
      <title>Setting up hyphenation</title>
      <p>FOP comes already with some hyphenation patterns.
If you need a hyphenation pattern which isn't included in the distribution, do the following:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Get the TeX hyphenation pattern file and turn it into an xml file which
conforms to the hyphenation.dtd in the subdirectory {fop-dir}/src/hyph.</li>
        <li>Name this new file following this schema: <code>languageCode_countryCode.xml</code>.
If you don't need a country code, leave it out, e.g. the file name for an American
english hyphenation pattern would look like this: <code>en_US.xml</code>.
For an Italian file: <code>it.xml</code>.
Language and country codes must be the same as in XSL-FO, that is follow <link href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/pub/ietf/http/related/iso639.txt">ISO 639</link> and
<link href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/pub/ietf/http/related/iso3166.txt">ISO 3166</link>
respectively.
NOTE: The ISO 639/ISO 3166 convention is that language names are
written in lower case, while country codes are written in upper case.</li>
        <li>If you have built your new hyphenation pattern file successfully there are
two ways to make it accessible to FOP.
          <ul>
            <li>Put this new file into the directory {fop-dir}/src/hyph and rebuild FOP. The file will be picked up and added to fop.jar.</li>
            <li>Put the file into a directory of your choice and specify this directory
in the userconfig.xml in the entry &lt;hyphenation-dir&gt;.</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <section id="hyphenation-sources">
        <title>Places to find TeX hyphenation pattern files</title>
        <p>The most important place to find hyphenation pattern file is the <fork href="http://www.ctan.org/tex-archive/language/hyphenation/">CTAN TeX Archive</fork>.</p>
      </section>
      <warning>You have to carefully check license issues when using hyphenation pattern files from other places.
The licenses of the files found on the Internet are not always clear.</warning>
      <note>Most of the files published in the CTAN Archive are licenced under the <fork href="http://www.latex-project.org/lppl.html">LaTeX Project Public License (LPPL)</fork>.
The Apache Foundation can't redistribute files under this license. If you want to use such a file you have to decide for yourself if you can use (and possibly distribute) the file under these conditions.</note>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
