<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN" "document-v11.dtd">

<document>
    <header>
        <title>Getting Involved</title>
        <subtitle>How to Get Involved in FOP</subtitle>
    </header>

    <body>
<section>
  <title>Getting involved</title>
  <p>
There are many different levels where people can get involved. The
development of FOP and the related plans and tasks are discussed on
the dev mailing list. Users can help or get issues resolved by
contributing information and examples to the developers.
</p>

  <section>
    <title>Get familiar with the Fop related standards</title>
  <p>
At the moment Fop is mainly a tool to render XSL:FO files to pdf.
Therefore if you want to contribute to Fop you should become
familiar with these standards. You can find links under
<link href="resources.html">Resources</link>.
</p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Fop's Design</title>
    <p>
The design for FOP is specified under the
<link href="design/index.html">Design</link> section.
    </p>
    <p>
This is where the information on how FOP is developed and designed
internally will be kept.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Subscribe to the fop developers list</title>
  <p>You can subscribe to fop-dev@xml.apache.org by sending an email
        to <link href="mailto:fop-dev-subscribe@xml.apache.org">fop-dev-subscribe@xml.apache.org</link></p>
  <p>Sending bug reports and feature requests to the list is a welcome and important contribution to
     developing Fop.  </p>
  <p>Read also the <link href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=fop-dev&amp;r=1&amp;w=2">archive</link>
     of the discussion list fop-dev to get an idea of the issues being discussed. </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Look at the developer's code using cvs</title>
  <p>Between releases the newest code can be accessed via cvs. To do this you need to install a cvs
     client on your computer, if it is not already there. An explanation how to connect to the
     Fop source repository can be found at <link href="http://xml.apache.org/cvs.html">http://xml.apache.org/cvs.html</link>.
     An introduction into cvs and the cvs manual can be found in the
     <link href="http://xml.apache.org/library.html">reference library</link>.</p>
  <p>All changes to the code repository are sent to a special mailing list. After a cvs commit the diffs are automatically sent to this list. You can subscribe
     to fop-cvs@xml.apache.org by sending an email to <link href="mailto:fop-cvs-subscribe@xml.apache.org">
     fop-cvs-subscribe@xml.apache.org</link>. If you want to contribute to the development of Fop you should subscribe,
     because it is important that you follow changes being made. </p>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Contributing code, tests and documentation</title>
  <p>If you want to contribute code (p.e. a bugfix), a test or documentation (p.e. an additional example), please do the following: </p>
  <p>1) Make sure your code doesn't break the existing one and that Fop still compiles.</p>
  <p>2) Create a file which shows the differences to the existing code.</p>
  <p>3) Send this file as an <strong>Attachment</strong> to <link href="mailto:fop-dev@xml.apache.org">fop-dev@xml.apache.org.</link></p>
  <p>One of the committers will test your code and commit it to the code repository.</p>
  <p>If you have a test or useful bug test you should <link href="testing.html">read this page</link>.</p>
  <p>BTW: The Apache project knows different roles for contributors, namely 'users', 'developers', 'committers' and the 'Project
     Management Committee' (An explanation of these roles can be found <link href="http://xml.apache.org/roles.html">here</link>).</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Coding Conventions</title>
  <p>As mentioned in <link href="http://xml.apache.org/source.html">Apache XML Project Guidelines</link>,
  <strong>all Java Language source code in the repository must be written in conformance to the</strong>
  <link href="http://java.sun.com/docs/codeconv/html/CodeConvTOC.doc.html">Code Conventions
  for the Java Programming Language</link> as published by Sun. Additionally we agreed on 4
  spaces (no tabs) for indenting.</p>
  <p>If you don't like those conventions, just use your own standards while developing and reformat the source before
  committing with a tool like <link href="http://astyle.sourceforge.net/">astyle</link> (Artistic Style).
  </p>
  </section>

</section>
    </body>
</document>

