<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN"
    "http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/xml-forrest/src/core/context/resources/schema/dtd/document-v12.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Implementing Properties</title>
    <authors>
      <person id="pbw" name="Peter B. West" email="pbwest@powerup.com.au"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>An alternative properties implementation</title>
      <note> 
        The following discussion focusses on the relationship between
        Flow Objects in the Flow Object tree, and properties.  There
        is no (or only passing) discussion of the relationship between
        properties and traits, and by extension, between properties
        and the Area tree.
      </note>
      <p>
        Property handling is complex and expensive. Varying numbers of
        properties <strong>apply</strong> to individual Flow Objects
        <strong>(FOs)</strong> in the <strong>FO tree </strong> but
        any property may effectively be assigned a value on any
        element of the tree.  If that property is inheritable, its
        defined value will then be available to any children of the
        defining FO.
      </p>
      <note>
        <em>(XSL 1.0 Rec)</em> <strong>5.1.4 Inheritance</strong>
        ...The inheritable properties can be placed on any formatting
        object.
      </note>
      <p>
        Even if the value is not inheritable, it may be accessed by
        its children through the <code>inherit</code> keyword or the
        <code>from-parent()</code> core function, and potentially by
        any of its descendents through the
        <code>from-nearest-specified-value()</code> core function.
      </p>
      <p>
        In addition to the assigned values of properties, almost every
        property has an <strong>initial value</strong> which is used
        when no value has been assigned.
      </p>
      <section>
        <title>The history problem</title>
        <p>
          The difficulty and expense of handling properties comes from
          this univeral inheritance possibility.  The list of properties
          which are assigned values on any particular <em>FO</em>
          element will not generally be large, but a current value is
          required for each property which applies to the <em>FO</em>
          being processed.
        </p>
        <p>
          The environment from which these values may be selected
          includes, for each <em>FO</em>, <strong>for each applicable
          property</strong>, the value assigned on this <em>FO</em>,
          the value which applied to the parent of this <em>FO</em>,
          the nearest value specified on an ancestor of this element,
          and the initial value of the property.
        </p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The construction hierarchy</title>
        <p>
          Properties are resoved in the <strong>FO tree</strong> in a
          strictly hierarchical manner.  Nodes are detected in the
          input in a <strong>pre-order</strong> traversal, and are
          built in the same order.  This imples that there are two
          phases, or states, of property resolution and construction.
          Any particular FO node is either in a state of constructing
          its own subtree, or in a stable state where the subtree
          construction is complete.  These states have differenct data
          requirements.
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dt>Subtree building</dt>
          <dd>
            In this state, all properties defined on this node, or any
            of its ancestors must be available to the subtree.  In
            effect, any property defined on this node must be
            available to its descendants, as all properties defined on
            any ancestor are available to this node.
          </dd>
          <dt>Stable: subtree building complete</dt>
          <dd>
            In this state, only the properties <strong>applicable to
            this node</strong> need be available.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Representing properties: &lt;property&gt; classes</title>
        <section>
          <title>Class vs instance</title>
          <p>
            What information is required of property objects?
            More particularly, what information is particular to the
            property classes, and what to the instantiated
            objects?  The answer to this question depend largely on
            how the property objects are used in the context
            of layout and Area tree construction.  The approach taken
            in this implementation is that properties are simply flags
            on certain data values associated with FOs.  The semantics
            of these flags are determined within the layout engine.
          </p>
          <p>
            Certain constant information attaches to individual
            property classes.  This information is detailed in
            the descriptions of individual properties in <em>Section
            7</em> of the specification.  Such information is
            represented in <strong>class</strong> fields and data
            structures within the classes.
          </p>
          <p>
            The "instance" information content of a property
            is:
          </p>
          <ul>
            <li>
              explicitly, the <code>PropertyValue</code> datum of
              the property, and
            </li>
            <li>
              implicitly, the <strong>Flow Object</strong> to which
              the property is attached.
            </li>
          </ul>
          <p>
            Properties, then, serve essentially to link <em>FO
            instances</em> with <em>PropertyValue instances</em>,
            attaching certain invariant semantic markers to the
            PropertyValues in the process.  In this implementation,
            these functions can be realised entirely within the
            property <strong>classes</strong> themselves,
            without the need to instantiate any objects.  In practice,
            <strong>property singletons</strong> are
            instantiated to make access to some invariants simpler.
          </p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <p>
        <strong>Next:</strong> <link href="classes-overview.html"
                                     >property classes overview.</link>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

