<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>


<s1 title="Extensions to FOP">
  <p>Sometimes it is desirable to have extensions to xsl:fo in order to support some feature of the 
     output format which isn't covered by the xsl:fo specification. 
     </p>
  <s2 title="Default Extensions">
<p>
These extension are available by default. They are automatically loaded
and you only need to provide the correct namespace for your embedded
xml markup.
</p>
  <s3 title="SVG">
<p>
Please see the <jump href="svg.html">SVG page</jump> for more details.
</p>
  </s3>
  <s3 title="Bookmarks">
     <p>To use this standard Fop extension, you need to add a namespace entry for
     http://xml.apache.org/fop/extensions on the root element. </p>

    <p>You can provide outlines inside the root object (but outside
       any page-sequences or
       other formatting objects). Here's an example of an outline entry:</p>
    <source>
<![CDATA[<fo:root xmlns:fo="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Format"
               xmlns:fox="http://xml.apache.org/fop/extensions">
  <fox:outline internal-destination="sec3">
    <fox:label>Running FOP</fox:label>

    <fox:outline internal-destination="sec3-1">
      <fox:label>Prerequisites</fox:label>
    </fox:outline>
  <fox:outline>
</fo:root>]]></source>
    <p>It works similarly to a basic-link. There is also an external-destination 
       property, but it isn't supported currently. See the pdfoutline.fo file in 
      docs/examples/fo for a more complete example.</p>
  </s3>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Adding Your Own">
<p>
To add your own extension you need to do the following things.
</p>
<p>
Write code that implements your extension functionality.
The easiest place to start is by looking at the code in org.apache.fop.extension.
</p>
<p>
Create a jar file with your classes, it must also include the following file "/META-INF/services/org.apache.fop.fo.ElementMapping". In this file you need to put the fully qualified classname of your element mappings class. This class must implement the "org.apache.fop.fo.ElementMapping" interface.
</p>
<p>
Create your fo file with the extra xml data embedded in the file with the correct name space. The examples for svg and pdfoutline.fo show how this can be done.
</p>
<p>
Put your jar file in the classpath and then run fop over the fo file.
</p>

  </s2>
</s1>

