<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!-- Overview -->

<document>
    <header>
        <title>FOP</title>
        <subtitle>XSL Formatter - Renderer in Java</subtitle>
        <authors>
        </authors>
    </header>

    <body>
<s1 title="FOP">
<p>
        <figure width="300" height="100" src="title.jpg" alt="FOP Title" />
</p>
    <p>FOP (Formatting Objects Processor) is the world's first print formatter driven by XSL formatting
       objects and the world's first output independent formatter. It is a
       Java application that reads a formatting object tree and then
       renders the resulting pages to a specified output. <jump href="output.html">Output formats</jump>
       currently supported are PDF, PCL, PS, SVG, XML (area tree representation),
       Print, AWT, MIF and TXT.
       The primary output target is PDF.
    </p>
<p>
        <figure width="480" height="260" src="document.jpg" alt="Render Diagram" />
</p>
    <p>The latest version of Fop is 0.20.3 and it supports the
       <jump href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2001/REC-xsl-20011015/">XSL-FO Version 1.0
       W3C Recommendation</jump>.
       You can <jump href="download.html">download</jump> 
       Fop including a precompiled version, the source code and many example files to 
       get you started. Pointers to introductions into xsl:fo can be found in the
       <jump href="resources.html">resources</jump> section. Please be aware, that 
       Fop is at the moment not a full implementation of the basic conformance level
       of the xsl:fo standard. You can find a list of supported flow objects and properties
       in the section <jump href="implemented.html">Features</jump> and in section 
       <jump href="limitations.html">Limitations</jump> in what way this support is 
       limited. 
    </p>
    <p>FOP is part of Apache's XML project. The homepage of FOP is 
       <jump href="http://xml.apache.org/fop">http://xml.apache.org/fop</jump>.
       Here you can find information about using and developing with FOP.
    </p>
    <p>Users can subscribe to fop-user@xml.apache.org by sending an email
        to <jump href="mailto:fop-user-subscribe@xml.apache.org">fop-user-subscribe@xml.apache.org</jump>
        this is where user specific topics are discussed.
     </p>
  </s1>

  <s1 title="Formatting">
<p>
        <figure width="480" height="260" src="layout.jpg" alt="Formatting Diagram" />
</p>
<p>
This image is a demonstration of a two page document. The xml data on the left
is formatted into the two pages on the right. The document contains static areas
that appear on every page, an external graphic in this case an svg document.
There is a footnote on the first page and a table that goes across both pages.
</p>
<p>
The advantage of XSL is the ability to take an XML document and to format
the information into a page layout. The XML document can be generated
in any way, the most common would be to use XSLT. FOP takes the XML
and formats the data into pages. The pages are then rendered to the
requested output.
</p>
<p>
This is a real document. The image was created by rendering the document
to the svg renderer then putting the rendered pages into an svg document
along with the xml.
</p>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Status">
<p>
        <figure width="585" height="175" src="track.png" alt="Planning and branches of FOP development" />
</p>
<p>
This is the development status of FOP. A branch has been created for
maintenance releases while the development is done to address various
performance and design issues.
</p>
<p>
Maintenance releases will be done as necessary. Another maintenance release
is planned for the near future to provide some fixes and to provide
compatibilty with <jump href="http://xml.apache.org/batik/">Batik</jump>
version 1.5 beta2. Other changes are: new hyphentaion patterns, changed
to use Avalon Logger interface and added background image support.
</p>
<p>
Development for 1.0DR1 is addressing the design issues for layout and
performance. This is focusing on making it possible to be conformant
to the spec and be able to handle large documents. This is roughly
30% towards a developers release that should have: similar functionality to
previous FOP releases, a rough API and a suitable design for developers
to work on more functionality.
</p>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="FOP Objectives">
    <p>The goals of the Apache XML FOP Project are to deliver an XSL FO->PDF formatter that is compliant to at least the Basic
       conformance level described in the W3C Recommendation from 15 October 2001, and that complies with the 11 March 1999 Portable Document
       Format Specification (Version 1.3) from Adobe Systems. 
    </p>

    <p>Conformance to the XML 1.0 Recommendation, XSLT 1.0 Recommendation and the XML Namespaces Recommendation is
       understood. Other relevant documents, such as the XPath and XLink Working Drafts, are referenced as necessary. The FOP
       Project will attempt to use the latest version of evolving specifications.
    </p>

   <p>To reach this aim currently the layout system is being redesigned to
better handle the formatting of all different types of formatting objects.
   </p>
  </s1>

    </body>
</document>

