<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<known-issues>
      <known-issue>
        MIF and SVG output support have not been restored, yet.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        Java2D/AWT support has been improved, but some problems remain,
        for example with block-containers.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        Auto table layout is not implemented, yet.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        The collapsing border model on tables is not implemented, yet. Please 
        use border-collapse="separate" for now.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        Footnotes may overlap with text of the region-body in multi-column 
        documents.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        Space resolution does not work between footnote regions.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        There's a problem involving nested block-containers and 
        reference-orientation 180/-180 (<a href="http://issues.apache.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=36391">Bugzilla #36391</a>)
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        block-containers with no height currently don't create a fence for
        spaces as they should (they behave like a normal block).
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        Preserved linefeeds in fo:character are not handled correctly.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        An empty block currently produces a fence for stacking constraints
        which it shouldn't.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        There are several small problems around white space handling.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        Images currently don't shrink so they fit on a page when they are 
        too big and shrinking is allowed to happen.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        inline-container may not work as expected.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        letter-spacing and word-spacing properties may not work as expected.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        leaders with leader-pattern="use-content" may not work as expected.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        keep-with-previous doesn't work inside tables and lists, yet.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        If two consecutive pages don't have the same available width, the 
        content currently isn't properly fit into the available space on
        the new page.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        background-images on page-number-citations are not placed correctly.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        Not all FO elements can be referenced by their "id", most notably:
        table-body, table-header, table-footer and table-row.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        The backgrounds of table-body, table-header, table-footer and 
        table-column are not painted, yet.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        Border and padding conditionality are not supported on table-cells, yet.
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        Column balancing in multi-column documents may not work as expected
        (<a href="http://issues.apache.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=36356">Bugzilla #36356</a>)
      </known-issue>
      <known-issue>
        Internal basic-links don't point to the exact location on a page, yet, as they
        did in 0.20.5. Currently you land in the upper left corner of the page.
      </known-issue>
</known-issues>
