<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>


<!-- Compiling FOP -->

<s1 title="Compiling FOP">
  <s2 title="Prerequisites">
    <s3 title="Java 1.1.x or later">
      <p>If you use Java 1.1.x you must also seperately include the swing classes, which can
         be found at the <jump href="http://java.sun.com/products/jfc/#download-swing">
         Sun website</jump>. From Java 1.2 on (aka Java 2) they are part of the standard 
         distribution. 
      </p>
    </s3>
    <s3 title="An XML parser">
      <p>An XML parser which supports Sax and DOM like 
         <jump href="http://xml.apache.org/xerces-j/index.html">Xerces-J</jump>.
         The parser must be in your classpath</p>
    </s3>
    <s3 title="The xslt processor Xalan ">
      <p>Some of the Java source code in FOP is generated from XML using
         XSLT. Xalan must be used to generate this code.</p>
      <p>Xalan is an XSL stylesheet processor written in java. At the moment you
         can't use any other processor, because the make process makes use of some
         proprietary features of Xalan which allow to write output in more
         then one document. You can find Xalan also at <jump href="http://xml.apache.org/xalan/overview.html">
        xml.apache.org</jump>. You have to use Xalan version 0.19.5 or later.
         Xalan.jar must be in your classpath and also the file bsf.jar, which comes with Xalan.</p>
    </s3>
    <s3 title="Setting of JAVA_HOME">
      <p>You have to set the enviroment variable JAVA_HOME. It must point to your local JDK 
      root directory. This is true, even if you use JDK 1.2 or above, which don't need this 
      setting. It is used by the compilation software.</p>
    </s3>
    <s3 title="Settings in your classpath">
      <p>If you want Fop to use the image library jimi, it should be in your classpath during 
         compilation. 
      </p>
      <p>A CLASSPATH for a complete compilation of Fop could look like this, if all these jar files are in 
         a directory called jars (example uses windows syntax):
      </p>
      <p><code>set CLASSPATH=\jars\xalan.jar;\jars\xerces.jar;\jars\bsf.jar;\jars\jimi.jar;
      </code></p>
    </s3>
    </s2>
  <s2 title="Compiling">
    <p>Compilation is started by executing build, either as a batch file on win32 (build.bat) or as a shell script on unix. The compilation uses Ant, 
       a replacement of make (you can find more information about Ant at 
       <jump href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">jakarte.apache.org</jump>).
        build.xml is the replacement of makefile. Look there for further information. </p>
       <p>A help screen is shown by calling "build usage".
    </p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Problems">
    <p>If you have problems compiling Fop, please try this first: delete the build directory completely and
       try a new build from scratch. Check, whether you have all necessary libraries in your classpath:
       xerces.jar, xalan.jar, bsf.jar, jimi.jar (optional). If you still have problems, please look at the
       page <jump href="bugs.html">bugs</jump>, for further help.
    </p>
  </s2>

  <s2 title="Compiling FOP on MacOS">
    <!-- contributed by Arved Sandstrom who also manages the webpage the jump points to -->
    <p>We strongly recommend the use of Codewarrior Java. You will find 
       a link to more information in the near future.
    </p>
  </s2>
</s1>
