<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!-- Status of Design/Rewrite -->

<document>
    <header>
        <title>Design Status</title>
        <subtitle>Current Status of FOP and Design</subtitle>
        <authors>
            <person name="Keiron Liddle" email="keiron@aftexsw.com"/>
        </authors>
    </header>

    <body>
<s1 title="Status">
<p>
Currently some of FOP is being re-written so that the layout can be handled
properly without the problems that have been encountered and to make
it possible to handle keeps/breaks and spacing better.
  </p>
<p>
A number of issues have been dealt with in the redesigned code.
  </p>
  </s1>
<s1 title="Features TODO">
<p>
<ul>
<li>avalon integration - logging, configuration, component management, caching, uri resolver</li>
<li>improved interfaces
<ul>
  <li>no threading/static problems</li>
  <li>simpler to use</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>better commandline handling</li>
</ul>
  </p>
  </s1>
<s1 title="Done/Started Features">
<p>
Many of these changes will make FOP much better to use and develop.
So if you help out with the development you can get to use these
things sooner.
<ul>
<li><strong>better layout design</strong> - that can handle keeps and
spacing better</li>
<li><strong>better area tree handling</strong> - means it can run in
less memory</li>
<li><strong>better image handling</strong> - redone so it can use a
cache and synchronizes properly only on the current image while loading</li>
<li>svg now in an xml handler, FOP can be used without batik</li>
<li>bookmark extension improved a bit - changed bookmark extension,
now requires a wrapping element bookmark</li>
<li>new interface for structured documents, rtf and mif</li>
<li>better handling of unknown xml and xml from an unknown namespace</li>
<li>Changed extensions to allow for external xml</li>
<li>Can have a default element mapping for extensions</li>
<li>mathml extension</li>
<li>another xml -> svg extension</li>
<li>svg text normal text if that can be handled otherwise stroked
this is done automatically</li>
<li>new area tree model</li>
<li>new renderer model</li>
<li>added handlers for xml in renderer</li>
<li>changed area tree xml format to match the area tree hierarchy</li>
</ul>

  </p>
  </s1>

    </body>
</document>

