<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!--
<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "../xml-docs/dtd/document-v10.dtd">
-->

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Property classes overview</title>
    <authors>
      <person id="pbw" name="Peter B. West"
	      email="pbwest@powerup.com.au"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <!-- one of (anchor s1) -->
    <s1 title="Classes overview">
      <s2 title="The class of all properties">
	<p>
	  If individual properties can have a "virtual reality" on the
	  stack, where is the stack itself to be instantiated?  One
	  possibility is to have the stacks as <code>static</code> 
	  data structures within the individual property classes.
	  However, the reduction of individual property instances to
	  stack entries allows the possibility of further
	  virtualization of property classes.  If the individual
	  properties can be represented by an integer, i.e. a
	  <code>static final int</code>, the set of individual
	  property stacks can be collected together into one array.
	  Where to put such an overall collection?  Creating an
	  über-class to accommodate everything that applies to
	  property classes as a whole allows this array to be defined
	  as a <em><code>static final</code> something[]</em>.
	</p>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="The overall property classes">
	<p>
	  This approach has been taken for the experimental code.
	  Rather than simply creating a overall class containing
	  common elements of properties and acting as a superclass,
	  advantage has been taken of the facility for nesting of
	  top-level classes.  All of the individual property classes
	  are nested within the <code>Properties</code> class.
	  This has advantages and disadvantages.
	</p>
	<dl>
	  <dt>Disadvantages</dt>
	  <dd>
	    The file becomes extremely cumbersome.  This can cause
	    problems with "intelligent" editors.  E.g.
	    <em>XEmacs</em>  syntax highlighting virtually grinds to a
	    halt with the current version of this file.<br/> <br/>

	    Possible problems with IDEs.  There may be speed problems
	    or even overflow problems with various IDEs.  The current
	    version of this and related files had only been tried with
	    the <em>[X]Emacs JDE</em>  environment, without difficulties
	    apart from the editor speed problems mentioned
	    above.<br/> <br/>

	    Retro look and feel.  Not the done Java thing.<br/> <br/>
	  </dd>
	  <dt>Advantages</dt>
	  <dd>
	    Everything to do with properties in the one place (more or
	    less.)<br/> <br/>

	    Eliminates the need for a large part of the (sometimes)
	    necessary evil of code generation.  The One Big File of
	    <code>foproperties.xml</code>, with its ancillary xsl, is
	    absorbed into the One Bigger File of
	    <code>Properties.java</code>.  The huge advantage of this
	    is that it <strong>is</strong>  Java.
	  </dd>
	</dl>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="The property information classes">
	<p>
	  In fact, in order to keep the size of the file down to more
	  a more manageable level, the property information classes of
	  static data and methods have been split tentatively into
	  three:
	</p>
	<figure src="PropertyStaticsOverview.png" alt="Top level
		property classes"/>
	<dl>
	  <dt><link href="PropNames.html">PropNames</link></dt>
	  <dd>
	    Contains an array, <code>propertyNames</code>, of the names of
	    all properties, and a set of enumeration constants, one
	    for each property name in the <code>PropertyNames</code> 
	    array.  These constants index the name of the properties
	    in <code>propertyNames</code>, and must be manually kept in
	    sync with the entries in the array. (This was the last of
	    the classes split off from the original single class;
	    hence the naming tiredness.)
	    <br/> <br/>
	  </dd>
	  <dt><link href="PropertyConsts.html">PropertyConsts</link></dt>
	  <dd>
	    Contains two basic sets of data:<br/>
	    Property-indexed arrays and property set
	    definitions.<br/> <br/>

	    <strong>Property-indexed arrays</strong>  are elaborations
	    of the property indexing idea discussed in relation to the
	    arrays of property stacks.  One of the arrays is<br/> <br/>

	    <code>public static final LinkedList[]
	    propertyStacks</code><br/> <br/>

	    This is an array of stacks, implemented as
	    <code>LinkedList</code>s, one for each property.<br/> <br/>

	    The other arrays provide indexed access to fields which
	    are, in most cases, common to all of the properties.  An
	    exception is<br/> <br/>

	    <code>public static final Method[]
	      complexMethods</code><br/> <br/>

	    which contains a reference to the method
	    <code>complex()</code>  which is only defined for
	    properties which have complex value parsing requirements.
	    It is likely that a similar array will be defined for
	    properties which allow a value of <em>auto</em>.<br/> <br/>

	    The property-indexed arrays are initialized by
	    <code>static</code>  initializers in this class.  The
	    <code>PropNames</code>  class and
	    <code>Properties</code> 
	    nested classes are scanned in order to obtain or derive
	    the data necessary for initialization.<br/> <br/>

	    <strong>Property set definitions</strong>  are
	    <code>HashSet</code>s of properties (represented by
	    integer constants) which belong to each of the categories
	    of properties defined.  They are used to simplify the
	    assignment of property sets to individual FOs.
	    Representative <code>HashSet</code>s include
	    <em>backgroundProps</em>  and
	    <em>tableProps</em>.<br/> <br/>
	  </dd>
	  <dt><link href="Properties.html">Properties</link></dt>
	  <dd>
	     <br/>
	    This class contains only sets of constants for use by the
	    individual property classes, but it also importantly
	    serves as a container for all of the property classes, and
	    some convenience pseudo-property classes.<br/> <br/>

	    <strong>Constants sets</strong>  include:<br/> <br/>

	    <em>Datatype constants</em>. A bitmap set of
	    integer constants over a possible range of 2^0 to 2^31
	    (represented as -2147483648).  E.g.<br/>
	    INTEGER = 1<br/>
	    ENUM = 524288<br/> <br/>
	    Some of the definitions are bit-ORed
	    combinations of the basic values.  Used to set the
	    <em>dataTypes</em>  field of the property
	    classes.<br/> <br/>

	    <em>Trait mapping constants</em>. A bitmap set of
	    integer constants over a possible range of 2^0 to 2^31
	    (represented as -2147483648), representing the manner in
	    which a property maps into a <em>trait</em>.  Used to set
	    the <code>traitMapping</code>  field of the property
	    classes.<br/> <br/>

	    <em>Initial value constants</em>. A sequence of
	    integer constants representing the datatype of the initial
	    value of a property.  Used to set the
	    <code>initialValueType</code>  field of the property
	    classes.<br/> <br/>

	    <em>Inheritance value constants</em>. A sequence
	    of integer constants representing the way in which the
	    property is normally inherited.  Used to set the
	    <code>inherited</code>  field of the property
	    classes.<br/> <br/>

	    <strong>Nested property classes</strong>.  The
	    <em>Properties</em>  class serves as the holding pen for
	    all of the individual property classes, and for property
	    pseudo-classes which contain data common to a number of
	    actual properties, e.g. <em>ColorCommon</em>.
	  </dd>
	</dl>
      </s2>
      <p>
	<strong>Previous:</strong> <link href=
	"alt.properties.html" >alt.properties</link>
      </p>
      <p>
	<strong>Next:</strong> <link href=
	"properties-classes.html" >Properties classes</link>
      </p>
    </s1>
  </body>
</document>
