<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>


<!-- Embedding FOP -->

<s1 title="Embedding FOP ">
  <s2 title="Overview">
  <p>Instantiate org.apache.fop.apps.Driver. Once this class is 
     instantiated, methods are called to set the
     Renderer to use
     and the OutputStream to use to output the results of the
     rendering (where applicable). In the case of the Renderer and
     ElementMapping(s), the Driver may be supplied either with the
     object itself, or the name of the class, in which case Driver will
     instantiate the class itself. The advantage of the latter is it
     enables runtime determination of Renderer and ElementMapping(s).
  </p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Examples">
  <p>The simplest way to use Driver is to instantiate it with the 
     InputSource and OutputStream, then set the renderer desired and 
     call the run method.
  </p>
  <p>Here is an example use of Driver which outputs PDF:
  </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
   Driver driver = new Driver(new InputSource (args[0]), 
                              new FileOutputStream(args[1]));
   driver.setRenderer(RENDER_PDF);
   driver.run();]]></source>

  <p>You also need to set the Logger for logging messages, see
     <jump href="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon/logkit/index.html">Jakarta Logkit</jump>
     for more information.
  </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    Hierarchy hierarchy = Hierarchy.getDefaultHierarchy();
    PatternFormatter formatter = new PatternFormatter(
       "[%{priority}]: %{message}\n%{throwable}" );

    LogTarget target = null;
    target = new StreamTarget(System.out, formatter);

    hierarchy.setDefaultLogTarget(target);
    log = hierarchy.getLoggerFor("fop");
    log.setPriority(Priority.INFO);
    driver.setLogger(log);]]></source>

  <p>To setup the user config file you can do the following
  </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
   userConfigFile = new File(userConfig);
   options = new Options(userConfigFile);]]></source>

  <p>Once the Driver is set up, the render method
     is called. Depending on whether DOM or SAX is being used, the
     invocation of the method is either render(Document) or
     render(Parser, InputSource) respectively.
  </p>
  <p>A third possibility may be used to build the FO Tree, namely
     calling getContentHandler() and firing the SAX events yourself.
  </p>
  <p>Once the FO Tree is built, the format() and render() methods may be
     called in that order.
  </p>
  <p>Here is an example use of Driver:</p>
  <source><![CDATA[
  Driver driver = new Driver();
  driver.setRenderer(Driver.RENDER_PDF);
  driver.setInputSource(new FileInputSource(args[0]));
  driver.setOutputStream(new FileOutputStream(args[1]));
  driver.run();]]></source>
  <p>You can also specify an xml and xsl file for the input.
  </p>
  <p>Here is an example use of Driver with the XSLTInputHandler:</p>
  <source><![CDATA[
  Driver driver = new Driver();
  driver.setRenderer(Driver.RENDER_PDF);
  InputHandler inputHandler = new XSLTInputHandler(xmlFile, xslFile);
  XMLReader parser = inputHandler.getParser();
  driver.setOutputStream(new FileOutputStream(outFile));
  driver.render(parser, inputHandler.getInputSource());]]></source>
  <p>Have a look at the classes CommandLineStarter or FopServlet for complete examples.</p>
<p>
<note>If your FO files contain SVG then batik will be used. When batik is
initialised it uses certain classes in <code>java.awt</code> that
intialises the java AWT classes. This means that a daemon thread
is created by the jvm and on unix it will need to connect to a
DISPLAY.
The thread means that the java application will not automatically quit
when finished, you will need to call <code>System.exit</code>. These
issues should be fixed in the upcoming JDK1.4</note>
</p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Hints">
     <p>
If FOP is going to be used multiple times within your application
it may be useful to reuse certain objects to save time.
     </p>
     <p>
The renderers and the driver can both be reused. A renderer is reusable
once the previous render has been completed. The driver is reuseable
after the rendering is complete and the reset method is called.
You will need to setup the driver again with a new OutputStream,
IntputStream and renderer.
     </p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Using Fop in a servlet">  
     <p>In the directory xml-fop/docs/examples/embedding you can find a working example how to use
        Fop in a servlet. You can drop the fop.war into the webapps directory of Tomcat, then 
        go to a URL like this:
     </p>
     <p>http://localhost:8080/fop/fop?fo=/home/path/to/fofile.fo</p>
     <p>You can also find the source code there in the file FopServlet.java</p>
     <p>
        To compile this code you will need servlet_2_2.jar (or compatible), fop.jar and the sax api in your classpath.
     </p>
  </s2>
</s1>


