<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!-- TODO -->
<document>
    <header>
        <title>TODO</title>
        <subtitle>TODO list for FOP</subtitle>
        <authors>
        </authors>
    </header>

    <body>

<s1 title="TODO List for FOP">
  <s2 title="FOP TODO">
    <p>
Core Features - these are the areas that are important to getting fop
to be useable for general use.
    </p>
    <p>
Processing improvements - these are mainly things that can be improved
in the way fop works, eg. resources usage, pdf output etc.
    </p>
    <p>
Enhancements - these are added functionality that might be useful, no
comment is made about the suitability of these suggestions.
    </p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Core Features">
<s3 title="Layout">
    <p>
The design for the layout is being developed under the
<jump href="design/index.html">Design</jump> section.
The details should be discussed on the dev mailing list.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="Property Support">
    <p>
Currently all properties are in the xml file. We need to handle all default
values properly (including ones that change depending on the element) and
all possible values.
    </p>
    <p>
To see if a property is implemented then look in the src/codegen/foproperties.xml file.
    </p>
    <p>
To see if a particular element uses this property then look in the element code. This is generally found in the package org.apache.fop.fo.flow.*.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="Property Resolution">
    <p>
This is support for the functions in property values that evaluate some
expression.
Better support for resolution including support for "inherit" and values
with lists.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="Examples">
    <p>
Better and more available examples for users and new people to get a
feel for what FOP does.
    </p>
</s3>
</s2>
  <s2 title="Processing Improvements">
<s3 title="Image Handling">
    <p>
Needs to be a bit more solid. Images are not cached properly
and image formats are not well documented.
Allow for direct insertion of jpeg images in svg into the pdf.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="Configuration">
    <p>
A better configuration setup that users can easily integrate.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="More PDF Outputs">
    <p>
Support for streaming and linearized pdf to help with different
deployement of pdf documents.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="i18n in awt viewer">
    <p>
Use proper i18n handling for awt viewer.
    </p>
</s3>
</s2>
  <s2 title="Enhancements">
<s3 title="font handling">
    <p>
Need better handling of font names, since a font can have several names.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="user agent">
    <p>
A user agent (or some similar thing) is needed to handle adjustable
values, such as setting dpi resolution.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="input from url">
    <p>
be able to specify a url as the input fo (or xml, xsl) documents.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="improve text handling in svg">
    <p>
support (better) the direct rendering of text into pdf graphics
and other similair outputs
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="stream encoding">
    <p>
Support for different encoding on different types of streams
in pdf document.
For example images and text.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="PDF Graphic State">
    <p>
Add support for the pdf graphic state for use with transparency
in pdf 1.4.
    </p>
</s3>
<s3 title="svg features">
    <p>
Currently patterns and gradients are not generated properly
    </p>
</s3>
  </s2>


</s1>
    </body>
</document>

