<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN"
    "http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/xml-forrest/src/core/context/resources/schema/dtd/document-v12.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Implementing footnotes</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Peter B. West" email="pbwest@powerup.com.au"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Implementing footnotes in FOP</title>
      <p>  
        Footnotes present difficulties for page layout primarily
        because their point of invocation in the flow is different
        from their point of appearance in the area tree.  All of the
        content lines of a footnote may appear on the same page as its
        invocation point, all may appear on a following page, or the
        lines may be split over a page or pages.  (This characteristic
        leads to another problem when a footnote overflows the last
        page of flow content, but that difficulty will not be 
        discussed here.)  This note considers some aspects of the
        implementation of footnotes in a galley-based design.
      </p>
      <section>
        <title>Footnotes and galleys</title>
        <p>
          In the structure described in the <link href= "galleys.html"
          >introduction to FOP galleys</link>, footnotes would be
          pre-processed as galleys themselves, but they would remain
          attached as subtrees to their points of invocation in the
          main text.  Allocation to a footnote-reference-area would
          only occur in the resolution to Area nodes.
        </p>
        <p>
          When footnotes are introduced, the communication between
          galleys and layout manager, as mentioned <link href=
          "galleys.html#pre-processing" >above</link>, would be
          affected.  The returned information would two b-p-d values:
          the primary line-area b-p-d impact and the footnote b-p-d
          impact.  The distinction is necessary for two reasons; to
          alert the layout manager to the first footnote of the page,
          and because the footnote b-p-d will always impact the
          main-reference-area b-p-d, whereas the primary inline-area
          may not, e.g. in the case of multiple span-areas.
        </p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Multiple columns and footnotes</title>
        <note> 
          A possible method for multi-column layout and balancing
          with footnotes, using a galley-based approach.
        </note>
        <p>
          This note assumes a galley, as discussed <link href=
          "galleys.html" >elsewhere</link>, flowing text with
          footnotes and possibly other blocks into a possibly
          multi-column area.  The logic of flowing into multiple
          columns is trivially applied to a single column.  The galley
          is manipulated within the context of the <em>layout
          tree</em>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Associated with the galley are two sets of data.
          One contains the maps of all "natural" break-points and
          the of all hyphenation break-points.  This set is
          constructed at the time of construction of the galley and
          is a constant for a given galley.  The second contains
          dynamic data which represents one possible attempt to lay
          out the galley.  There may be multiple sets of such data
          to reflect varying attempts.  The data of this set are,
          essentially, representations of line-areas, with the supporting
          information necessary to determine these line-areas.
        </p>
        <p>
          The line-area data includes the boundaries within the
          galley of each line-area, the boundaries of each column
          and the boundaries of the "page", or main area.  When a
          line-area boundary occurs at a hyphenation point, a
          "virtual hyphen" is assumed and accounted for in the
          i-p-d.  As mentioned, individual footnote galleys will
          hang from the parent galley.  The associated data of the
          footnote galleys is similar: a once-only break-points map,
          and one or more line-area maps.  No column boundaries are
          required, but a page boundary is required at the end of
          the last footnote or where a footnote breaks across a page
          boundary.
        </p>
        <p>
          A number of b-p-d values are also maintained.  For each
          line-area, the b-p-d, the main area b-p-d increment, the
          footnote b-p-d increment and the footnote's page-related
          b-p-d increment are required.  The main-area b-p-d
          increments for any particular line-area are dependent on
          the column position of the line-area.  Total b-p-d's are
          also kept: total footnote b-p-d, total main area b-p-d,
          and totals for each column.<br/><br/>
          <strong>Figure 1</strong> Columns before first footnote.
        </p>
        <figure src=
        "images/design/alt.design/initial-column-values.png" alt=
        "Columns before first footnote"/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Balancing columns</title>
        <p>
          <strong>Figure 2</strong> Adding a line area with first
          footnote.
        </p>
        <figure src= "images/design/alt.design/line-area-5.png"
                alt= "Columns after adding first footnote"/>
        <p>
          Columns are balanced dynamically in the galley preliminary
          layout.  While the galley retains its basic linear
          structure, the accompanying data structures accomplish
          column distribution and balancing.  As each line-area is
          added, the columns are re-balanced.  <strong>N.B.</strong>
          This re-balancing involves only some of the dynamic data
          associated with the participating galley(s).  The data
          structures associating breakpoints with the beginning and
          end of individual line areas does not change in
          re-balancing; only the association of line-area with column,
          and, possibly, the various impact values for each line-area.
          <br/><br/>
          <strong>Figure 3</strong> Adding a line area with next
          footnote.
        </p>
        <figure src= "images/design/alt.design/line-area-6.png"
                alt= "Columns after adding next footnote"/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Layout managers in the flow of control</title>
        <note>To be developed.</note>
      </section>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

