<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.1//EN"
    "http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/xml-forrest/src/resources/schema/dtd/document-v11.dtd">

<document>
    <header>
    <title>FOP Alternative Design</title>
    <subtitle>Alternative Design Approach to FOP</subtitle>
    <version>$Revision$ $Name$</version>
    <authors>
      <person name="Peter B. West" email="pbwest@powerup.com.au"/>
    </authors>
    </header>
    <body>
    <section>
      <title>Alternative Design</title>
      <p>
  This section of the FOP web site contains notes on approaches
  to an alternative design for FOP.  The individual documents
  here are fragmentary, being notes of particular issues,
  without an overall framework as yet. 
      </p>
      <p>
  The main aims of this redesign effort are:
      </p>
      <ul>
  <li>full conformance with the Recommendation</li>
  <li>increased performance</li> 
  <li>reduced memory footprint</li> 
  <li>no limitation on the size of files</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
  In order to achieve these aims, the primary areas
  of design interest are:
      </p>
      <ul>
  <li>
    Representing properties, for most purposes, as integers.
  </li>
  <li>
    Distributing FOP processing over a number of threads with
    single-point downstream communication and flow control by
    means of traditional producer/consumer queues.  The threads
    so far under consideration are:
    <ul>
      <li>XML parser</li>
      <li>FO tree builder</li>
      <li>layout engine</li>
      <li>Area tree builder</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    Representing trees with explicit Tree objects, rather than
    as implicit relationships among other objects.
  </li>
  <li>
    Caching integrated into the tree node access methods.
  </li>
      </ul>
      <section>
        <title>Status and availability</title> 
  <p>
    The <em>ALT DESIGN</em> effort is not taking place on the
    main line of development, represented by the <em>HEAD</em>
    tag on the CVS trunk.  The source is available via the
    FOP_0-20-0_Alt-Design tag.  This code has only a crude,
    non-<em>Ant</em> build environment, and is expected only to
    compile at this stage.  Only the parser stage and the first
    stage of FO tree building is present.  However, the first
    example of producer/consumer binding is working, the Tree
    class with inner Tree.Node and inner
    Tree.Node.<em>iterators</em> classes are available and
    working.  Property handling is quite advanced, and is likely
    to be almost complete some time in July, 2002.
  </p>
  <p>
    Only <link href="mailto:pbwest@powerup.com.au">Peter
    West</link> is working on the ALT DESIGN sub-project.
  </p>
      </section>
    </section>
    </body>
</document>

